John Wesley Hyatt Collection
John Wesley Hyatt Collection
circa 1869-1945
Hyatt, John W. (John Wesley), 1837-1920.
1 linear ft.
Collection consists of the Executive Committee Meeting Minutes of the Celluloid Company, 1890 to 1905, two bound volumes of patents obtained by John Wesley Hyatt, including one for the first celluloid billiard ball and several other patents for billiard ball coatings and knife-handles; a booklet on Hyatt's acceptance of the Perkin Medal, 1914; six photographic portraits; and a relief sculpture of the John Wesley Hyatt commemorative award.
2651125
Biographical History
John Wesley Hyatt (1837-1920) was an American manufacturer in the plastics field, and the inventor of celluloid.
Born in Starkey, New York in 1837, at the age of 16 Hyatt began work as a printer in Illinois and later in Albany, New York, where he eventually set up his own manufacturing company which became the Albany Billiard Ball Company. In his experiments, Hyatt discovered the solvent action of camphor on cellulose nitrate under moderate heat and pressure, creating celluloid. This was the basis of his 1870 patent. He also developed the necessary machinery for working his new material.
One of the first uses of the new plastics material was for making denture plates and Hyatt formed the Albany Dental Plate Company in 1870. In 1872, its name was changed to the Celluloid Manufacturing Company and in 1873 the company moved to in Newark, New Jersey.
Hyatt was awarded the Perkin Gold Medal in 1914, given by the Society of the Chemical Industry, and was posthumously inducted into the Plastics Hall of Fame in 1974.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Wesley Hyatt Collection consists of the Executive Committee meeting minutes of the Celluloid Company, 1890 to 1905; two bound volumes of patents obtained by John Wesley Hyatt, including one for the first celluloid billiard ball and three seperate patents regarding billiard balls, knife-handles, and other articles; six photographic portraits of Hyatt; and a booklet on Hyatt's acceptance of the Perkin Medal, 1914. Also included is a relief sculpture by Paul Manship of the John Wesley Hyatt commemorative award.
Related Material
has numerous holdings in the areas of plastics and industrial design. Please refer to for a complete listing. There are also related artifacts.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Plastics; Hyatt, John W. (John Wesley), 1837-1920.; Celluloid Manufacturing Company.; Plastics Hall of Fame.; Celluloid.; Billiards -- Equipment and supplies.; Patents.; Plastics industry and trade.; Minutes (administrative records); Patents.; Programs (documents); Photographs.; Manufacturers.; Inventors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from National Plastics Center and Museum, 11/06/2008. Originally, gift of Dewey Rainville and James DeBenedetto, and of the John Wesley Hyatt family
Inventory
- Legal
  - Patents, 1869; 1871,; 1907; "improvement in processes of coating billiard balls, knife-handles, and other articles" with drawings, "improved method of coating billiard balls, &c." and an agreement between John Wesley Hyatt, H. Parker Marshall, Albert H. Sanborn, Joseph G. Spurr and Albert Albright Jr. involving billiard balls (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - John Wesley Hyatt, undated; two distinct black and white portraits; 6 prints (Box 1)
- Sculpture
  - Relief sculpture by Paul Manship, [1945]; Model for the John Wesley Hyatt commemorative award (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Celluloid Company, Executive Committee meeting minutes, December 17, 1890 through February 21, 1905; leather bound, handwritten ledger; includes report on the September 4, 1898 fire (Box 1)
  - Patents, 1883-1918; late 19th century; 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - Perkins medal and acceptance speech, 1914 (Box 1)
  - Purple award ribbon, undated (Box 1)
  - Tupperware managers seminar ribbon, 1954 (Box 1)